Welcome to Dealmakers. I'm Sarah Sharp.
I'm a real deal attorney who helps
people buy and sell businesses every
day. And I'm going to tell you one of
the things that's probably in your
letter of intent makes you look like an
idiot and makes your sellers think that
you're not qualified to run their
business. So you in this scenario have a
letter of intent and maybe you've sent a
lot of them out and you haven't gotten a
lot of feedback or you've gotten just
kind of a rope decline, decline,
decline. Now you're wondering what you
might be doing wrong and it could be
nothing cuz that just happens sometimes.
There is one mistake that I see that's
being perpetuated all over this YouTube
platform and LinkedIn and I want to get
in front of it right now. Before I jump
in though, if you do find this content
valuable, please like and subscribe or
share it with your friends and neighbors
and check out dealacademy.org for some
courses on how you can become the expert
on the deal process and not have to rely
on other folks to do all that for you.
So, what are you missing? What are you
doing wrong? There is a mythical unicorn
term out there that is 0% interest on a
seller financed deal. I don't know who
started thinking that that was a thing
that really happens, but I've seen a lot
of folks come across my desk thinking
that that is an attractive offer, which
is neither here nor there. But even if a
100% seller finance deal is just not a
thing that happens at any interest rate,
if you are making an offer and a portion
of that offer is either going to come
from the bank or it's going to be cash
that the seller receives at closing in
any other way and then a portion of that
offer is going to be a note, a loan
document where the seller is basically
loaning you money to be paid back later.
That's called a seller note. If you're
going to have portion of your deal, it's
a seller note or seller finance, you
need an interest rate for that loan
document. And for some reason, a lot of
folks think that 0% interest loans are a
thing and they make you look really
silly if you don't know that they're not
a good idea. So why aren't they a good
idea? Why doesn't the seller like them?
I mean, it's not just a financial thing.
So yes, the seller wants more money and
interest rate secures that for them.
Another reason relatedly is the seller
wants to think that if you get a chance,
you might pay them back. And if you have
a 0% loan, it would never make financial
sense for you to pay that back. You
should ride that out and make the
minimum payments until the very last
payment date. So, that's not attractive
from a deal structure perspective, but
that's not really the thing that makes
you look dumb. I mean, that's just a
less attractive deal term. Every deal
offering has those. Well, what makes you
look silly is that you haven't
identified that that brings a lot of
risk into play for the seller because
they might be subject to or they will be
subject to imputed interest income,
which is a concept that the IRS uses to
say anybody who gets a below market loan
has to pay taxes as though they made
interest at a market rate. So, what does
that mean? Unless you're subject to one
of very narrow exceptions. If you have a
loan principle of $100,000 and the
applicable federal rate, Google it. You
have short-term, midterm, long-term
loans that you can cross reference and
figure out what the feds think the fair
market rate is. Let's say that that's
4%. So, if the applicable rate is 4% and
you had a 2% loan on $100,000, then you
were supposed to make $4,000 on that and
interest, but you made two. So, you're
going to be paying taxes as though you
made four. So, if you have a $10,000
loan principal, AFR is 3%, the interest
actually paid is 200, you're going to
pay 100. Your taxes as though you paid
you got paid an additional 100. So,
there's a tax liability. Obviously, when
you have a 0% loan, there's a quite big
difference between 0%, especially if
there's a pretty hefty loan principle.
There's quite a big difference between
0% on several hundred,000 and 4.5% on
several hundred,000. So, that's real tax
liability that's borne by the seller.
That's one of the reasons that people
don't really like it when there's a 0%
interest loan. Obviously, we also have
cost of living increases and everything
like that. So, with inflation, you
really it's almost a reverse interest
rate if you're at 0%. But that is why a
smart offer will at least address that
by saying AFR, applicable federal rate
is the bare minimum interest that
they'll pay on that seller note. If you
do offer a 0% loan, you're asking the
seller to take on that tax liability in
addition to loaning you money at a cost
to them essentially, in addition to the
risks associated with it. It's very
unattractive and it comes across poorly.
You can still survive with it if you
explain what you're doing. And it really
helps if you at least know what AFR is,
what imputed interest income is, and the
general risk that you're asking the
seller to take. If that's news to you
for the first time, don't put it in your
LOI. Make a better offer or at least
have your seller financing be at the
applicable federal rate so that you take
that off the table altogether. If you
found this valuable at all, please like
and subscribe or check out
dealacademy.org